<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- name="GENERATOR" content="github.com/mmarkdown/mmark Mmark Markdown Processor - mmark.miek.nl" -->
<rfc version="3" category="info" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-bertocci-identity-in-browser-00" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" consensus="true">

<front>
<title abbrev="browser-use-cases">Identity Use Cases in Browser Catalog</title><seriesInfo value="draft-bertocci-identity-in-browser-00" stream="IETF" status="info" name="Internet-Draft"></seriesInfo>
<author initials="V." surname="Bertocci" fullname="Vittorio Bertocci"><organization>auth0.com</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>vittorio@auth0.com</email>
</address></author>
<author initials="G." surname="Fletcher" fullname="George Fletcher"><organization>Verizon Media</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>gffletch@aol.com</email>
</address></author>
<date year="2021" month="January" day="4"></date>
<area>Security</area>
<workgroup>Web Authorization Protocol</workgroup>
<keyword>security</keyword>
<keyword>oauth2</keyword>
<keyword>best current practice</keyword>

<abstract>
<t>This informational document aims to gather in a single place all the most important scenarios in which identity protocols in current use leverage web browser features to achieve their goals and deliver their intended user experience.
The purpose of compiling this scenario collection is to make it easier for the identity community to engage with the browser vendors, and in particular to preserve (or enhance) user experience and expressive power of the identity protocols in mainstream use as browsers introduce new privacy preserving restrictions and new identity tailored features.
By providing a single artifact, listing scenarios in a consistent format, we hope to anchor the conversation on concrete outcomes and impact of changes on end users, developers, providers and in general everyone contributing to identity in the industry.</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="overview"><name>Overview</name>
<t>As attempts to profile and track user activities on the web intensify, leading to increasingly egregious privacy violations, browser vendors introduce new constraints meant to thwart known tracking techniques.
As they do so, however, they often end up breaking legitimate use cases as well- with identity protocols features such as single sign on, token renewals and the like being disptoportionally affected.
Conscious of those effects and committed to preserve user experience, browser vendors are working on dedicated identity API that aim at preserving and enhancing the user experience in identity transactions, without relying on the general purpose artifacts on which current identity protocols depend on.
One key challenge that is emerging in the process is that browser vendors tend to design around a limited set of well-known, consumer-only use cases, classifying most other cases as enterprise use cases hence solvable by exceptions and local business policies, whereas that is often not the case (e.g., single sign on is a common requirements across web properties even for consumer services, such as online managines form the same publisher) or the expected solutions (e.g. companies deploying MDM and managing policies on their employees and contributors machines) are not always viable. Discussions between browser vendors and identity experts are not always easy, and are frequently repeated whenever the individuals and initiatives involved change. This makes progress difficult.
This infomational document is a collection of use cases in which identity protocols depend on web browser features to perform their intended function. By gathering the main use cases in a single, shared artifact, and by describing every use case thru a fixed schema designed to surface the most salient characteristics germane to the identity-browser features discussion, we aim to provide a tool to facilitate conversations between browser vendors and identity experts.
This is meant to be a living document, constantly gathering and discussing scenarios contribuitions (via dedicated GitHub repository and OAuth working group mailing list) and periodically incorporating new entries in the main document. The contribution process is described in {{contributionprocess}}.</t>

<section anchor="scope"><name>Scope</name>
<t>This document considers in scope scenarios and use cases for which all the following requirements apply:
- must be in common use, represent a common practice, a behavior of products in widespread adoption, etc.
- can be from any mainstream identity and authorization protocol specification, regardless of standard bodies affiliation: e.g. OAuth, OpenID Connect, SAML, etc.
- must require use of browser features (e.g. cookies, redirects, decorated links, HTTP headers, local storage etc) for at least part of its sequence of messages.
- can involve, but isn't limited to: establishing a user session, obtaining credentials and intermediate artifacts (e.g. OAuth2 authorization codes).</t>
<t>The following is considered out of scope:
- any scenario or protocol not currently in mainstream use, regardless of standardization status.
- any scenario not using a web broweser in any capacity.
- proposing new browser behaviors or API, or identity scenarios using hypothetical new browser capabilities. The goal of this project is to document what's already in place, to inform discussions about what's next taking place in forums shared with the browser vendors.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="conventions-and-definitions"><name>Conventions and Definitions</name>
<t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;, &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;, &quot;SHOULD&quot;,
&quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;NOT RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;MAY&quot;, and &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this
document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 {{RFC2119}} {{!RFC8174}}
when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="contributionprocess"><name>Contribution Process</name>
<t>Before submitting feedback and contributions, please familiarize yourself with our current issues list and review the <eref target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/wg/oauth/documents/">working
group home page</eref>. If you're
new to this, you may also want to read the <eref target="https://www.ietf.org/tao.html">Tao of the
IETF</eref>.</t>
<t>Be aware that all contributions to the specification fall under the &quot;NOTE WELL&quot;
terms outlined <eref target="https://www.ietf.org/about/note-well/">here</eref>.</t>
<t>This informational draft is meant to be a living document, where new scenarios and refinement of the current ones will keep being added as needed.
This work originated in the <eref target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/wg/oauth/documents/">IETF working group for OAuth</eref>, however we hope to gather contributions from the entire identity community, regardless of affiliation.
Most of the work will happen on <eref target="https://github.com/IDBrowserUseCases/docs">https://github.com/IDBrowserUseCases/docs</eref>, a GitHub repository meant to facilitate contributions from the community as summarized below.</t>

<section anchor="contributing-scenarios"><name>Contributing Scenarios</name>
<t>Each scenario is captured in a document following the template described in {{usecasestemplate}}.
You can find all contributed scenarios in <eref target="https://github.com/IDBrowserUseCases/docs/tree/main/src/">docs/src/scenarios</eref>.
If you want to contribute a new scenario:
1. Please read the preamble in this section and ensure that you meet all requirements
2. Verify that your scenario isn't already captured in any of the documents in <eref target="https://github.com/IDBrowserUseCases/docs/tree/main/src/scenarios">docs/src/scenarios</eref>. If it is a variant of an already captured scenario, please consider bringing it up on the <eref target="https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/oauth">mailing list</eref> instead.
3. If your scenario is new, please fork the repo and create a local copy of SCENARIOTEMPLATE.md, renaming your file to match the format protocolname_protocolscenario.md
4. Edit your local copy by filing the appropriate sections of the template, see {{usecasestemplate}} for details.
5. Once you are ready, please submit a PR to add the new doc to the scenarios folder
6. Monitor the <eref target="https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/oauth">mailing list</eref> for discussions and requests for clarification</t>
</section>

<section anchor="discussing-scenarios-details-and-inclusion"><name>Discussing Scenarios Details and Inclusion</name>
<t>All submissions will be discussed on the <eref target="https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/oauth">mailing list</eref>, possibly undergoing revisions according to the feedback, and once rough consensus is reached, the scenario will be included in this informational document.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="usecasestemplate"><name>The Use Case Template</name>
</section>

<section anchor="scenarios"><name>Scenarios</name>

<section anchor="todo-scenario-title"><name>TODO Scenario Title</name>
<t>TODO Brief description of the scenario.</t>

<section anchor="summary"><name>Summary</name>

<section anchor="contributor"><name>Contributor</name>

<ul>
<li><t>Name: TODO</t>
</li>
<li><t>Organization: TODO</t>
</li>
<li><t>Email: TODO</t>
</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="protocol"><name>Protocol</name>

<ul>
<li><t>Name: TODO SAML|OIDC|OAUTH2|Other(specify)</t>
</li>
<li><t>Grant/flow (if applicable): TODO eg. Implicit|Hybrid|AuthCode|SAMLArtifact|etc</t>
</li>
<li><t>Reference: TODO aa <eref target="https://linktospecandsection">https://linktospecandsection</eref></t>
</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="browser-features-required"><name>Browser Features Required</name>
<t>todo: delete all the ones that don't apply, add anything not listed
- 1st party Cookie
- 3rd party cookies
- Redirect with link decoration
- Form post
- Local Storage
- IFrames
- JavaScript</t>

<section anchor="target-audience"><name>Target Audience</name>
<t>todo: delete all the ones that don't apply, add anything not listed
- B2C
- B2E
- B2B
- G2C</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="adoption"><name>Adoption</name>
<t>TODO Enumeration of products, industries, vendors that rely on this scenario as described.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="description-of-the-flow"><name>Description Of The Flow</name>
<t>TODO long form description of the flow, including start state, end state, and sequence diagram when possible</t>
</section>

<section anchor="intended-user-experience"><name>Intended User Experience</name>
<t>TODO long form description of the intended user experience, with particular attention on the desired outcomes (eg no visible prompt in SSO scenarios)</t>
</section>

<section anchor="privacy-considerations"><name>Privacy Considerations</name>
<t>TODO long form description of privacy characteristics of the scenario, with particular attention to aspects affecting the browser (eg presence of browser-readable artifacts carrying user info, use of global|pairwise|no identifiers, etc).</t>
</section>

<section anchor="miscellaneous"><name>Miscellaneous</name>
<t>TODO anything not fitting any of the sections above that is relevant for understanding how the scenario might be affected by browser changes.</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="Acknowledgements"><name>Acknowledgements</name>
</section>

<section anchor="IANA"><name>IANA Considerations</name>
<t>This draft includes no request to IANA.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="Security"><name>Security Considerations</name>
<t>This document has no security considerations. Readers should refer to the security considerations of the specifications references by each of the individual use cases.</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>

</back>

</rfc>
